Guide to the Chester Loomis papers, 1813-1865.
Loomis, Chester papers, 1813-1865.
- Series IV. Political papers and letters
  - From A. B. Coffin re Naples Road, Dec. 7, 1852 (Box 6)
  - From John Lapham asking for influence with Governor Seymour, Dec. 9, 1852 (Box 6)
  - From D. W. C. Gage requesting recommendation for post in Customs House, May 10, 1853 (Box 6)
  - From A. B. Coffin requesting recommendation for office of J. P. in Gorham, Apr. 7, 1853 (Box 6)
  - From A. B. Coffin, Apri1 11, 1853 (Box 6)
  - From Williams Ansley, Fairfax County, Virginia speech made at Democratic rally by "extra Bi1l who defended repeal of Missouri Compromise, Oct. 30, 1856 (Box 7)
  - Draft of letter to Ontario Messenger re slavery, 1856 (Box 7)
  - From John Lapham requesting influence in getting nomination for Commissioner of Loans, Jan. 6, 1857 (Box 7)
  - From Thomas M. Howell re appointment as district attorney for northern district, of New York, Aug. 14, 1857 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Feb. 23, 1858 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Mar. 31, 1858 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Apr. 2, 1858 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Apr. 9, 1858 (Box 7)
  - From Frank Loomis re Lincoln and Douglas, Apr. 9, 1858 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Nov. 8, 1853 (Box 6)
  - Draft of letter (7) re Republican Party, Sept. 6, 1859 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Feb. 6, 1860 (Box 7)
  - Draft of letter to Horace Greeley, Feb. 12, 1860 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Feb. 20, 1860 (Box 7)
  - From E,. B. Pottle in Washington, Mar. 6, 1860 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Mar. 12, 1860 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, July 30, 1860 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Jan. 23, 1861 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Feb. 19, 1861 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Feb. 23, 1861 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Mar. 9, 1861 (Box 7)
  - From Harvey Hobart, Mar. 15, 1861 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Mar. 25, 1861 (Box 7)
  - From Harvey Hobart, Aug. 30, 1861 (Box 7)
  - From Harvey Hobart, Nov. 18, 1861 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Laomis, Feb. 6, 1862 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Feb. 12, 1862 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Feb. 15, 1862 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Feb. 23, 1862 (Box 7)
  - From Charles A. Loomis, Mar. 1, 1862 (Box 7)
- Series V. Letters and papers regarding legal matters
  - Edward P. Clark & Augustus Whitney v. John Sutfun & Thomas Van Buren, record of proceedings, June 29, 1840 (Box 4)
  - Edward A. McKay v. Otis Pierce, deposition, Sept. 1, 1843 (Box 4)
  - Edward A, McKay v. Otis Pierce, subpoena, Sept. 2, 1843 (Box 4)
  - Edward A. McKay v. Otis Pierce, settlement, Sept. 8, 1843 (Box 4)
  - Benedict & Co. v. Barker, affidavit, Oct. 17, 1843 (Box 4)
  - Francis Harris v. Benjamin Weast, deposition and summons, Oct. 23, 1843 (Box 4)
  - Francis Harris v. Benjamin Weast, deposition and account of proceedings, Nov. 25, 1843 (Box 4)
  - Francis Harris v. Benjamin Weast, deposition, Nov. 30, 1843 (Box 4)
  - Francis Harris v. Benjamin Weast, summons to jurors, Dec. 4, 1843 (Box 4)
  - Deposition of Otis Pierce, 1843 (Box 4)
  - Jonathan Lincoln v. Alvin Benham, affidavit and summons, Jan. 9, 1844 (Box 5)
  - The People v. Enoch Barker, affidavit, Jan. 16, 1844 (Box 5)
  - David Lamorsux v. Morris Clark, affidavit, Jan. 25, 1844 (Box 5)
  - Bond of Morris Clark, Feb. 6, 1844 (Box 5)
  - Coonrod Fisher v. David Francisco, summons, Mar. 20, 1844 (Box 5)
  - Coonrod Fisher v. David Francisco, affidavit, Mar. 26, 1844 (Box 5)
  - Coonrod Fisher v. David Francisco, affidavit, Mar. 30, 1844 (Box 5)
  - Coonrod Fisher v. David Francisco, account of proceedings, Apr. 4, 1844 (Box 5)
  - Coonrod Fisher v. David Francisco, warrant of restitution, Apr. 8, 1844 (Box 5)
  - David Lamoreux v. Morris Clark, deposition, Apr. 30, 1844 (Box 5)
  - Heirs of Thomas Hulbert jr. v. David J. McMaster, summonses, Oct. 16, 1844 (Box 5)
  - Heirs of Thomas Hulbert jr. v. David J. McMaster, arbitration and account of proceedings, Oct. 22, 1844 (Box 5)
  - Heirs of Thomas Hulbert jr. v. David J. McMaster, account, 1844 (Box 5)
  - Levi Hotchkiss v. Henry S. "Otto, affidavit, July 31, 1845 (Box 5)
  - Levi Hotchkiss v. Henry S. Otto, arrest warrant, Aug. 2, 1845 (Box 5)
  - Levi Hotchkiss y_. Henry S. Otto, subpoenas and deposition, Aug. 9, 1845 (Box 5)
  - Levi Hotchkiss y_. Henry S. Otto, account of proceedings and Otto's bond to Hotchkiss, Aug. 25, 1845 (Box 5)
  - Recognizance of Daniel Mclntyre, William Mclntyre, and John Grosbeck in assault and battery case, Sept. 3, 1845 (Box 5)
  - Notice to Alvin Benham to remove, Oct. 13, 1846 (Box 5)
  - Philip Gregory v. Alanson Watkins, declaration and pleadings, Feb. 21, 1847 (Box 5)
  - Job Bocline v. Michael Sisk, deposition and summons, Apr. 8, 1847 (Box 5)
  - Francis Harris v. Moses Page, affidavit, June 1, 1847 (Box 5)
  - John Chamberlain v. Daniel Francisco, bill of costs, June 29, 1847 (Box 5)
  - Philip Gregory v. Alanson Watkins, reference and withdrawal, Aug. 23, 1847 (Box 5)
  - Philip Gregory v. Alanson Watkins, reference and report, Aug. 24, 1847 (Box 5)
  - Chamberlain v. Francisco supra, letter, Feb. 8, 1849 (Box 5)
  - Marvin Power & Peter Cameron v. Samuel Fisk & Electra Fuller, arbitration, Mar. 12, 1850 (Box 6)
  - Letter from John Chamberlain, July 29, 1851 (Box 6)
  - Letter from John Chamberlain, Dec. 2, 1851 (Box 6)
  - John Percival v. Levi S. Loomis, Sally Green, and Chester Loomis, settlement of suit to recover money lent to Levi S. Loomis May 20, 1846, June 25, 1852 (Box 6)
  - Michael Francisco v. Joshua Fitch, jr., re estate of Cornelius DeWitt, bill of particulars, Aug. 23, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Michael Francisco v. Joshua Fitch, jr., decision, Aug. 28, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Michael Francisco v. Joshua Fitch, jr., referees ordered to submit new report; new report, Oct. 18, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Michael Francisco v. Joshua Fitch, jr., copy of Supreme Court opinion (case reversed and remanded ), Sept. 1, 1857 (Box 7)
  - Michael Francisco v. Joshua Fitch, jr., decision by referees for Francisco, Aug. 24, 1853 (Box 6)
- Series VI. Letters and papers regarding claims for bounty and pension from veterans of War of 1812
  - Lorana Arnold, Apr. 14, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Benjamin Blodget, Dec. 12, 1853 (Box 6)
  - Ephraim Blodget., June 23, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Wi11iam Blodget, June 23, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Betsey Boardman, June 28, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Betsey Boardman, July 24, 1856 (Box 7)
  - Joseph Chase, Apr. 24, 1854 (Box 6)
  - Jonathan Comstock, Apr. 14, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Jane Dumbolton, Aug. 14, 1854 (Box 6)
  - Jane Dumbolton, Sept. 6, 1854 (Box 6)
  - Adam Fake, Jan. 15, 1858 (Box 7)
  - Adam Fake, Oct. 15, 1859 (Box 7)
  - Christopher Fisher, Apr. 14, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Samuel Fisk, Apr. 25, 1855 (Box 7)
  - C. Francisco, Apr. 14, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Martha Gilbert, June 6, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Benjamin Green, Apr. 14, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Betsey Green, June 17, 1854 (Box 6)
  - Deborah Green, Apr. 17, 1854 (Box 6)
  - Deborah Green, May 6, 1854 (Box 6)
  - Elizabeth Hinckley, Oct. 19, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Elizabeth Hinckley, May 10, 1856 (Box 7)
  - Amy Hilt, May 10, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Amy Hilt, Jan. 16, 1856 (Box 7)
  - F. H. Johnson, July 25, 1852 (Box 6)
  - John Lee, Apr. 8, 1851 (Box 6)
  - John Lee, Feb. 27, 1852 (Box 6)
  - Polly Lee (widow of Ebenezer Welch), Sept. 23, 1858 (Box 7)
  - James Loomis, Sept. 24, 1853 (Box 6)
  - James Loomis, Dec. 30, 1853 (Box 6)
  - Philomena Moffatt, May 5, 1855 (Box 7)
  - William Morrison, Mar. 20, 1846 (Box 5)
  - William Morrison, May 13, 1846 (Box 5)
  - Mary Pearce, Apr. 10, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Samuel Pearce, Oct. 30, 1856 (Box 7)
  - Ephraim Phelps, Sept. 13, 1851 (Box 6)
  - Heziah Robinson, June 28, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Heziah Robinson, July 24, 1856 (Box 7)
  - Louis Shares, Jan. 30, 1852 (Box 6)
  - Henry Torrey, June 11, 1855 (Box 7)
  - W. Welch, Mar. 17, 1858 (Box 7)
  - John W. Williams, Dec. 23, 1854 (Box 6)
  - John W. Williams, Dec. 25, 1854 (Box 6)
  - John W. Williams, Mar. 19, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Jacob Windnagle, Dec. 12, 1851 (Box 6)
  - Jacob Windnagle, Apr. 14, 1855 (Box 7)
  - Jacob Windnagle, Oct. 16, 1855 (Box 7)
- Series VII. Letters and papers regarding Geneva and Rushville Plank Road Company lawsuit
  - Resolution of directors of Plank Road Company to appoint a committee, consisting of Robert C. Nicholas, Phineas Prouty, Daniel B. Lindsley, and William T. Crittenden, to build toll houses, May 22, 1849 (Box 5)
  - Agreement between William Crittenden and William D. Raymond for construction of toll houses, June 9, 1849 (Box 5)
  - Letter from Crittenden to Nicholas re progress on road and houses, July 11, 1849 (Box 5)
  - Letter from Crittenden, Jan. 16, 1850 (Box 6)
  - Statement of Crittenden, Jan. 19, 1859 (Box 7)
  - Reference of accounts and claims between Plant; Road Company and William Crittenden; minutes of testimony, Jan. 19, 1850 (Box 6)
  - Decision, Apr. 16, 1850 (Box 6)
- Series VIII. Letters and papers regarding post office
  - Letter announcing suspension of stage operation between Naples and Canandaigua because of competition from steamboats an Canandaigua Lake, Apr. 17, 1829 (Box 1)
  - Letter re appointment of postmaster at East Bloomfield, Dec. 25, 1832 (Box 1)
  - Letter re A. Torrey, Nov. 30, 1837 (Box 2)
  - Letter re A. Torrey, Dec. 4, 1837 (Box 2)
  - Letter re Loomis' conduct as postmaster, May 2, 1838 (Box 3)
  - Draft of reply to May 2 letter, May 8, 1838 (Box 3)
  - Final account with past office, May 1841 (Box 4)
  - Copy of letter to F. Granger re conduct of Jonathan Pratt, Jr., during the latter 's assistantship at the Rushville post office in 1838, July 12, 1841 (Box 4)
- Series IX. Letters and papers regarding education
  - List of notes for collection due Geneva College, Jan. 1, 1827 (Box 1)
  - List of notes for collection due Geneva College; letter, Dec. 1830 (Box 1)
  - Re Geneva College, Feb. 6, 1832 (Box 1)
  - Re donations to Geneva College, Jan. 31, 1838 (Box 3)
  - Copy of letter to E. J. Roberts re. donation to college to be located near Loomis' land in St. Clair, Michigan, Sept. 6, 1837 (Box 2)
  - From Roberts, Oct. 23, 1837 (Box 2)
  - Copy of letter to Roberts, Nov. 20, 1837 (Box 2)
  - Copy of remonstrance against founding of an agricultural college, Feb. 15, 1851 (Box 6)
- Series X. Letters from and regarding William Ansley, Fairfax County, Virginia
  - Re repeal of Missouri Compromise, see p. 8, Oct. 30, 1856 (Box 7)
  - Letter, Jan. 1, 1857 (Box 7)
  - May 23, 1857 (Box 7)
  - Dec. 3, 1858 (Box 7)
  - Feb. 25, 1859 (Box 7)
  - Mar. 25, 1859 (Box 7)
  - Apr. 23, 1859 (Box 7)
  - Sept. 16, 1859 (Box 7)
  - Sept. 23, 1859 (Box 7)
  - Nov. 7, 1859 (Box 7)
  - Nov. 14, 1859 (Box 7)
  - Nov. 22, 1859 (Box 7)
  - Nov. 23, 1859 (Box 7)
  - Dec. 15, 1859 (Box 7)
  - Apr. 3, 1860 (Box 7)
  - Apr. 8, 1861 (Box 7)
  - Sept. 7, 1861 (Box 7)
  - Nov. 17, 1861 (Box 7)
- Series XI. Letters and accounts of Samuel Colt, Geneva (Ontario County)
  - Dec. 17, 1825 (Box 1)
  - Jan. 14, 1826 (Box 1)
  - Feb. 3, 1826 (Box 1)
  - 1826 (Box 1)
  - Feb. 3, 1827 (Box 1)
  - July 27, 1827 (Box 1)
  - Mar. 2, 1828 (Box 1)
  - Mar. 3, 1829 (Box 1)
  - Dec. 24, 1829 (Box 1)
  - Apr. 1830 (Box 1)
  - Feb. 3, 1831 (Box 1)
  - Apr. 17, 1831 (Box 1)
  - July 9, 1831 (Box 1)
- Series XII. Letters from Richard Gilbert regarding sale of pews in Rushville
  - Oct. 29, 1851 (Box 6)
  - Apr. 20, 1852 (Box 6)
  - Aug. 21, 1852 (Box 6)
- Series XIII. Papers regarding Rushville
  - Notice to Loomis as overseer of highways, district #51, to take charge of roadwork, May 29,1849 (Box 5)
  - Subscription of Rushville inhabitants to organize a cemetery, Feb. 5, 1855 (Box 7)
- Series XIV. Miscellaneous
  - Agreement with Hiram Torrey for construction of Loomis' house, Mar. 7, 1843 (Box 4)
  - Letter from superintendent of State Lunatic Asylum re Alvah Green's application on behalf of Rugg, Dec. 4, 1851 (Box 6)
  - Deed to Samuel Boots and Benjamin Boots, Romulus (Seneca County), from Ann El lice and children, Bath (Somerset County), England,, through their attorneys Barent and John Rutgers Bleecker, Albany, for land in Gorham (Ontario County) note added "Samuel Bootes [sic.] Great-grandfather of Burt C. Walther," Deed actually made 2-29-12, Mar. 13, 1813 (Box 1)
  - Folder of correspondence, 1843-1845 (Box 6)
- Series XV. Soldiers' Letters Civil War
  - Chester Loomis to Lieut. J. H. Brough, Aug. 23, 1862 (Box 7)
    Advice that Maurice O'Connell execute an allotment certificate for the support of his three children.
  - (overleaf) Lieut. J. H. Brough to Chester Loomis" (Camp Swift, Geneva), Aug. 24, 1862 (Box 7)
    Notification of O'Connell's signing an allotment of $10.00 per month for support of children also that bounty was sent home by Lyman Loomis.
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis, Sept. 9, 1862 (Box 7)
    Location of camp, 2 miles west of Harper's Ferry. Uncertain when fight will star surrounded on all sides. Men are in good health} the scarcity of money; desire that children be cared for.
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis (Camp Douglas, Chicago), Oct. 3, 1862 (Box 7)
    Report of surrender; stolen clothing -and goods; journey to Chicago and encampment conditions there; request for money; desire that children be cared for.
  - Tyler Brink to Chester Loomis (Chicago), Oct. 8, 1862 (Box 7)
    Request that Chest inquire whether or not Mr. Flinn has the money and booty which Tyler sent him.
  - Fayette Greene to Chester Loomis (Camp Douglas, Chicago), Oct. 9, 1862 (Box 7)
    Request for $25.00 to replace money and clothing which was stolen at surrender of Harper's Ferry; will repay $26.00 when paid.
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis (Camp Douglas, Chicago), Oct. 22, 1862 (Box 7)
    Request for money; quarters are very bad and the cold weather is coming. Report that he has received no answer to his previous letters.
  - M. O'Connell to Chester Loomis (Camp Douglas, Chicago), Nov. 3, 1862 (Box 7)
    Acknowledgement of CL's letter, very little prospect of coming home soon; concern of report by guardian of children, Mrs. Scott, of children's behavior; request that CL check them to see if the children should be taken to another place.
  - Fayette Greene to Chester Loomis (Camp Douglas, Chicago), Nov. 8, 1862 (Box 7)
    Request for $15.00; rumor that camp will move to New York State from Chicago; conditions of camp very poor; average of four deaths a day and many men in hospital; delight of seeing Rev.Hudson, CL's pastor.
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis (Washington), Dec. 19, 1862 (Box 7)
    Acknowledgement of CL's letter and $2.00; report that Burnside and his whole force had to retreat loss of 12,000 men; signs of fight coming insufficient supply of men; bad conditions of camp; impatient to finish war; personal thoughts of the war and the benefits being: a soldier; no money.
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis (Union Mills, Va.), Feb. 8, 1863 (Box 7)
    Received pay finally; request that CL see that children are provided for; many deaths in regiment; rumor that they will move but new location unknown; present location, Onion Mills.
  - Fayette Greene to Chester Loomis (Washington), Feb. 9, 1863 (Box 7)
    Allotment pay able to CL $27.00 and other financial matters; death of two Rushville boys.
  - Fayette Greene to Chester Loomis, Feb. 16, 1863 (Box 7)
    Request for $10.00 return because wallet was stolen from camp.
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis, Apr. 1, 1863 (Box 7)
    Report of moving to Centerville; possibility of fight soon; Condition of regimen desire to come home, but not without obtaining union of States lack of money.
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis., Apr. 26, 1863 (Box 7)
    Lack of money; unable send money for children; request for stamps; possibility of moving camp again
  - Fayette Greene to Chester Loomis (Centerville, Va.), May 16, 1863 (Box 7)
    Request for $5.00; weather is good.
  - Fayette Greene to Chester Loomis (Centerville, Va.), May 27, 1863 (Box 7)
    Acknowledgement of CL's letter; rumor that Bee has "flanked" Hocker and made him retreat; men are losing faith in Hocker; optimistic viewpoint even though conditions are bad; expecting attack by Stewart's Cavalry. *(Hooker)
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis (Centerville, Va.), June 5, 1863 (Box 7)
    Payment of allotment; praise for Grant; request for CL's opinion of the war.
  - Fayette Greene to Chester Loomis (Centerville, Va. ), June 11, 1863 (Box 7)
    Check was enclosed for $25.00; boys in good health; successes of troops.
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis (Centerville, Va. ), June 15, 1863 (Box 7)
    30,000 troops joined them at Centerville; Lee is on the move and are our men;" states that he would spend his time and over before He would settle with the South; request for $5.00 to use of Mar..
  - Blue slip giving statement of account of Fayette Greene, soldier, June 30, 1863 (Box 7)
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis, July 13, 1863 (Box 7)
    Acknowledgement of CL' letter and $5.00; Mar. from Centerville to Gettysburg; many men lost at battle in Gettysburg; rebs lost more men. Condition of soldiers following battle; spirits high; hopes he will be home soon, but not until the rebs are "cut up to pieces;" Brought is wounded.
  - Fayette Greene to Chester Loomis, July 14, 1863 (Box 7)
    Notice of mistake made by check payable to Judge Loomis instead of Chester Looms; says that if there is any trouble about it "send it to the Treasury of the U.S. and state the circumstances." Report that "rebs" have crossed the Potomac River; readiness; for battle; confidence that war will be over soon.
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Locals (near Warrenton Junction), Aug. 8, 1863 (Box 7)
    Acknowledgement of CL's latter; opinion that those boys who waited for the draft right up until the last minute do not make very good soldiers; rumor that his f friend, John, wounded at Gettysburg, had died, because his leg was amputated and he died after the operation.
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis (Rapidan River), Oct. 4, 1863 (Box 7)
    Scarcity of money; clothes lost or stolen often; thank you for the letter to Colonel Bull, but there is "no such thing' as a furlough in the array of the Potomac; rebs are on the other side of the river; tell children to be good.
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis, Sept. 3, 1863 (Box 7)
    Possibility of renewal of fight; request that CL write to James Bull, his colonel, to request a furlough so that he can come home and take care of the situations there with the children.
  - Fayette Greene to Chester Loomis (Rapidan River), Oct. 4, 1863 (Box 7)
    Check was enclosed ($30,00); request that CL put it on interest.
  - Fayette Greene to Chester Loomis (Warrenton, Va.), Nov. 5, 1863 (Box 7)
    Did not receive answer to last letter acknowledging $20.00; request for $2.00's worth of stamps; corps won two "brilliant victories."
  - Fayette Greene to Chester Loomis (near Brandy Station, Va. ), Nov. 15, 1863 (Box 7)
    Acknowledgement of CL's letter; enclosed check for $20.00 to be put on interest; brilliant victory after crossing the river; too many Copperheads; praise for North's response for the war as indicated by the last election.
  - Fayette Green to Chester Loomis (near Brandy Station, Va.), Nov. 25, 1863 (Box 7)
    -enclosed two-dollar notes; received no losses in their last campaign.
  - Fayette Green to Chester Loomis (near Brandy Station, Va. ), Dec. 3, 1863 (Box 7)
    -returned to old position after Mar.ing all night; Mead retreated after Lee received reinforcement; enclosed money not
  - Morris O'Connell to Chester Loomis (near Brandy Station, Va.), Jan. 1, 1864 (Box 7)
    Disturbed that his money which he bad sent CL had been stolen; furloughs were being granted, but are stopped again; some chance he might get one in winter; worried about care of children; if he came to Rushville, he would not have a place to stay and would have very little time to do anything about the children.
  - Fayette Green to Chester Loomis, Feb. 1864 (Box 7)
    Request for $2.00's worth of stamps.
  - William Francis to Chester Loomis (Washington), Apr. 18, 1864 (Box 7)
    Request for knowledge concerning situation of place for his wife to live.
  - Fayette Green to Chester Loomis, Aug. 3, 1864 (Box 7)
    Request for $14.00. (Baltimore)